all right so why should you listen to a
random guy standing in front of a
whiteboard with a white T-shirt on my
name is Matt I'm a current strategy
associate at Google prior to that was a
consultant at BCG and today I'm going to
explain to you how to do Market sizing
problems so first of all what even is
Market sizing well Market sizing is
essentially just a type of question that
you might get asked in consulting or
strategy case interviews where the
interviewer basically asks you a very
vague and oftentimes ambiguous question
that to people who aren't familiar with
might seem like it's impossible to do
for example questions like how big is
the market for dog toys or how many
windows are in New York City or even
what's the market for weddings in Canada
and so to someone who has never seen
these kinds of questions before if you
get asked this in an interview you're
probably going to freak out or freeze up
on the spot because you're going to
think to yourself what the heck I've
never seen this before how am I supposed
to do this why are they asking me this
and you'll just have a bunch of random
questions floating through your mind now
before I get into explaining an actual
example I want to talk about why a lot
of consulting firms use Market sizing as
an interview technique and it really
goes back to this concept of being able
to handle ambiguity SL structured
problem solving okay and so you might be
wondering why does this matter so much
well a lot of the times in Consulting
there are many situations where you're
given a very vague or ambiguous question
and your entire task as a junior
consultant is to literally take this
very vague question and get to an actual
answer while also receiving not much
guidance because what you have to
remember is a lot lot of times your
client is hiring you because they
themselves have tried to figure
something out and they don't know how to
do it but the other and more tactical
reason why consulting firms often test
Market sizing is because a big part of
our job especially if you are working on
a strategy project is understanding how
big the opportunity even is so for
example if you're working on a growth
strategy project where the client has
hired you to help them think about
potential ways to grow the business we
first need to understand and how big is
the market that this business is
operating in and sometimes you know
you'll have resources showing you oh the
market is x billion dollars but other
times you might be looking at a very
niche market where there might not be
very credible data and so you'll have to
do your own Market sizing exercise in
order to actually understand how big the
opportunity is also in case it wasn't
clear for those of you who actually
don't know what I'm talking about when I
say Market whenever people are talking
about a market they're literally often
talking about things in terms of either
total dollar amount or total volume and
I'm talking about transactions here so
if someone asks me about what is the
total market for weddings in Canada for
example the dollar amount would be okay
like what is the absolute highest amount
of money that could theoretically be
generated by people that are looking to
get married in Canada but anyways this
is a high level overview of why Market
sizing questions show up so often in
Consulting case interviews and the other
thing that we have to really understand
and that I want you to internalize
before we dive into an actual example
exle is that it's not about the numbers
it's about the approach okay and the
reason I say that is because when you're
in an interview situation and you're
asked this kind of a question what the
interviewer is trying to test is not
whether you can actually get to a
specific number they're actually trying
to test how you come up with your own
methodology and structure to coming to
that answer it's basically the same as
coming up with your own equation to
solve some sort of problem problem and
in this scenario it doesn't matter what
the end result is but it's more about
how did you make the equation and does
the equation even Mak sense for the
purposes of the question so from that
perspective two people could do the same
Market sizing question and they could
get completely different numbers like
wildly different numbers but one of them
could do far better because they have a
more logical and structured equation
that got them there versus the other
person that maybe didn't have as thought
out of an approach and so I'm now going
to walk through an example here here and
so I think we can just come up with our
own question which one I think is
relevant is how many students apply to
consulting jobs each year and let's just
say how many students in the US just to
make it simple okay so I've written down
the question and oftentimes if you're in
a case interview scenario what I
recommend is you first write down the
question so that you can ground yourself
and always go back to it and then I
would recommend just asking for a minute
or two to structure your thoughts and so
you can ask the interviewer and say hey
this sounds awesome can I have a minute
or two to put together some ideas and
they'll always say yes and you should go
ahead and start thinking about like the
quote unquote equation that I was
talking about earlier for how you would
get to the number before I walk through
the example best practices when you are
in a case interview and you get asked a
market sizing question is you really
want to First write down the question
and think of potential clarifying
questions that you can ask okay and so
oftentimes with these Market sizing
questions you want to really understand
what you're actually sizing and when I
say what are you actually sizing you
need to understand like for example I
the question is how many students in the
US apply to consulting jobs each year
and this is fairly specific but if you
were given a question like what is the
market for Consulting applications then
a clarifying question you might need to
ask is this dollars or is this number
vaps now in this case I've made the
question super specific so it's pretty
clear to me here that I am going to be
looking at number of students and not
some dollar figure but it's really good
to clarify whether you're going to be
sizing in terms of dollars or units the
second thing is if for example the
question didn't include in the US then
you might want to clarify okay are we
looking at the number of applications
from students in the US specifically or
globally or US and Canada what are we
specifically looking at here and so that
will also give you a better idea of what
you're even sizing in the first place
and another clarifying question that I
could ask for example is when we talking
about students is this only undergrads
or does this include grad students as
well right because there's going to be a
lot of mbas and phds that will be
applying to these consulting jobs as
well and let's just assume that in this
case it's just undergrads for the
purposes of simplicity so after we've
asked all these clarifying questions
then we can dive into the actual
building out of the structure AKA
creating that equation that I talked
about earlier and so I'm going to walk
you through it so the way I think about
it is we can start with the total number
of undergrads in the US and from there
we can work down to the percent of those
that are even interested in Consulting
in the first place because not everybody
is going to even be interested right and
from there I think there's a few
different things we can do I think that
we can actually split out this bucket
into the four different years so
freshman sophomore juniors and seniors
so what I might do is something like
freshman sophomores Juniors and then
obviously you have your seniors okay and
so what I've actually done here is
what's known as segmentation
segmentation drive that word into your
mind Consultants love to use it and it
simply means we are breaking out a
bigger group into segments that are
often characterized by specific
characteristics whether it be oftentimes
it's demographic characteristics but it
could be you know spending habits or
other characteristics related to
behavior and so what this is going to do
is break out this percentage of people
that are interested in Consulting into a
little bit more of a nuanced group of
four and so for example this bucket will
give us the total number of freshmen in
the US that are interested in Consulting
okay but that's not going to get us
exactly to the number of people who
actually apply and so what we need to do
is we need to First figure out the
percent of people that are eligible to
apply because not everyone can even
submit an application and then we need
to go down and figure out the percentage
that actually apply of those that are
eligible and only then will we get to
the number of students who apply to
Consulting roles in the US specifically
and so now we need to figure out like
within this bucket here for these four
groups like what percentages we actually
want to apply but before we put any
numbers to it once you have basically
put together the structure you should
walk your interviewer through it and ask
for feedback and so the way I would do
this is I would say awesome so I put
together a quick structure here would
love to get your thoughts basically I'm
thinking we can start with the total
number of undergrads in the US per year
and then we can apply a percentage
haircut to account for for only those
that are interested in Consulting
because not everyone who is a student is
obviously going to be interested in
consulting or even aware of it and then
from there I've segmented that group of
students that are interested in
Consulting into four different buckets
based on their year so we have our
freshman sophomore juniors and seniors
and I think this is important because
there are going to be different
characteristics based on what year they
are from there though we can apply a
percent to account for those that are
actually eligible to apply and then we
can apply another percent to account for
those that actually go through with
applying which ultimately gets us down
to our number of students in each year
that actually apply to consulting jobs
and the aggregate of those numbers is
going to be our total how does that
sound to you okay so invite them for
feedback and they will give you their
thoughts on whether you might be missing
something or if the structure even makes
sense and then before you actually start
doing anything you also want to see if
they have any numbers for you so for
example after they say yeah that sounds
good to me you might want to ask them
something like okay awesome do we happen
to have any information or data related
to any of these key buckets and
conveniently they might say something
like oh yeah so we actually know that
the total number of undergrads in the US
last year was around 15 million at the
very least you should hopefully at least
get a population number and if they
don't give you that then you can also
just say all right so that's okay I'm
going to reasonably assume that based on
my understanding of the US they're about
300 million people in us and I would
think that x amount would be students
does that sound okay and just be like
okay because again numbers really do not
matter in this kind of a question it's
more about the structure and how you
think about it but for this
demonstration today I know that last
year there was about 15 million
undergrads in the US in total but now
let's walk through the other numbers so
for the percentage that are interested
in Consulting here we're going to have
to guess but I think what might be
reasonable is less than 50% probably
closer to like 20% of people and I think
that makes sense because from my own
experience being a student in the past
obviously this depends on what type of
school you're at so certain schools will
skew in other ways but on average I
would say there's probably 20 to 30% of
people that are studying business and of
those there's a sizable proportion that
are interested in Consulting and so I
think that 20% number sounds reasonable
now when we move down to the percentage
eligible to apply this is where I think
it gets interesting because we're
thinking about either jobs like
full-time jobs out of undergrad for
consulting or internships nothing else
and potentially the occasional like
sophomore Diversity Program and so for
freshmen unfortunately I think 0% are
going to be eligible to apply I would
say sophomores is probably only like 10%
because again this is those diversity
programs that mckeny ban and BCG run
which from my experience they do not
take that many students but then come
junior year there's more opportunities
for people to apply for internships and
then Senior Year even more so I would
say maybe we can say 100% are eligible
to apply here and then 100% of seniors
are also eligible to apply that sounds
reasonable to me and then moving down to
the percentage that actually apply again
I would say like with the Freshman this
is not really I'm just going to put na
here because I don't think if you're
eligible you can even apply but for
sophomores Juniors and seniors I think
we can maybe say 2third of people apply
so 66% and also by the way when you're
explaining it to your interviewer why
you want to choose a certain percentage
always try to draw from your own
experience and just say well you know
from my own experience I've seen that X
number of people actually do this thing
and so that sounds reasonable to me and
as long as it's not like something crazy
that you're saying they'll be completely
fine with with it so let's just apply
66% and assume that 2/3 of people that
are eligible actually end up going
through with the application you know
putting the time into their resume cover
letter submitting the app blah blah blah
so now we have enough data to actually
get to an actual number and so again
we're going to start with this 15
million number we're going to apply 20%
to it AKA divide by 5 so that's about 3
million students and let's assume that
there's a equal distribution across all
four years so divide this by four to get
the number in each year which is about
750k in each ET okay and then obviously
with the Freshman 750k * 0% that's a
zero with sophomores we have 10% so
that's 75k take 2/3 of 75k that's 50k
with Juniors we're saying 100% are
eligible and then 2/3 of those AKA 500k
are actually applying similarly with
seniors also 500k and so now when we sum
up all four of these that gets us to
this 1.05 Million number here which is
basically 1 million let's just round and
immediately what you should do after you
get this number is you should be taking
a step back taking a deep breath and
just think about does this number even
make sense we have to sanity check it
and so how I would do this is I would go
back up to the top and say to myself or
explain to the interviewer actually
based on the 15 million total number of
undergrads in the US which we've paired
down to 3 million that actually are
interested in Consulting it looks like
based on our analysis that only about a
third are actually going through with
the application and that's that sounds
pretty reasonable to me based on my
personal experience not everyone who
says that they're going to apply to
something actually do we all have that
friend who says they're going to do
something but never does and so that's
how I would explain it to the
interviewer and it's important to note
that yes I've said that the numbers are
not as important and it's more about the
structure of the equation and that's
true but that's specifically for the
interview when you're actually on the
job in Consulting the amount of thought
that goes into the actual inputs is
immense and it's so important because
these are what are actually driving the
final number and so I think just
demonstrating to the interviewer that
you can be a little bit more thoughtful
about what numbers you're using and that
you can have a perspective on what the
final outcome is and whether or not it
sounds or seems reasonable to you is
going to go a long way now this is just
one way that you could approach this
problem of how many undergrad students
in the US apply to consulting jobs this
year but now let's think about what I
could do better and so how can I make
this better okay so I've just put down
some ideas for how I might be able to
make this better and fully recognizing
that there are always ways to improve
and so the first thing that I've written
down here is we can refine the inputs
now again I know I said that the numbers
don't really matter as much but if
there's any way that you can demonstrate
to your interviewer that you're at least
a little bit more thoughtful about the
inputs that go into it those go a really
long way so what's an example of that
well a great example is actually right
here with the percent of students that
actually apply in each year now I've
sort of standardized this across the
board and said that 6 6% across the
board actually apply minus the Freshman
but even something as simple as
increasing their percentage for seniors
because I would imagine that seniors
would be more desperate for a job than
Juniors and so probably a higher
proportion of them are actually going to
go through with applying because the
clock is ticking on them so maybe this
could go up to like a 80% instead of 66%
which would change your numbers but that
would just demonstrate that we're being
a little bit more thoughtful about the
behaviors between different years now
the second thing that we could do is we
could add in Greater detail to the
structure so I know that in the
beginning I clarified that this was only
asking about how many undergrad students
in the US were applying to consulting
jobs but theoretically if we wanted to
build this out into an even more robust
model we could also try to include
graduate students because again
consulting firms hire a ton of mbas and
phds and people with Advanced degrees
and so it's not really doing it justice
to leave those people out of the picture
similarly we could add in other
countries if the question wasn't only
specific to the US for example say it
was asking about the US and Canada then
we could factor in Canada as well and
again also this number down here this 1
million is only the number of students
that apply and so if we want to get to
an even more granular level of say the
number of applications we could even
apply like a average number of
applications per student who applies
that way we would have an additional
data point to look at and then finally
the third thing that you could think
about is do we want to completely
restructure the way that this is set up
right I have set it up so that you know
we start with the total number of
students and then we split it eventually
into these four groups based on year and
then we go down but hypothetically we
could structure this a completely
different way where maybe we don't split
it up by year and so these are just some
things to consider as you work through
Market sizing questions they get a lot
easier with practice and so don't worry
if you're not getting it just yet but
that said if you are having trouble with
your casing and you think you would
benefit from a little bit more help I do
offer personalized one-on-one coaching
where I can give you more specific
feedback related to your context if that
sounds interesting to you then feel free
to check out the Link in the description
but otherwise thanks again for being
here I'll see you guys in the next one
peace